Guide to the Helen Follett Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Helen Follett papers,
1919-1969
[Bulk Dates: 1928-1939]
Follett, Helen (Helen Thomas)
2.94 linear ft. (7 document boxes)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
MS#0440
4078772
Helen Thomas Follett’s papers consist primarily of personal letters and business correspondence, manuscripts of published and unpublished works, publicity items for her books, newspaper clippings, photographs, and postcards. In addition, there are manuscripts, correspondence, and newspaper clippings related to her oldest daughter, Barbara Newhall Follett.
Biographical Note
Helen Thomas Follett was born in 1893 and was an early twentieth-century author of young adult books. Her first two books, Magic Portholes and Stars to Steer By, were based on her sailing trip to the Caribbean and the South Seas islands during the late 1920s with her teen-age daughter, Barbara.
Follett advocated the use of typewriters in elementary schools as a teaching tool for young students to help learn words and form sentences. She had moderate success with her writings and had two more works published, Third-Class Ticket to Heaven and House Afire! in 1939 and 1941 respectively.
She was married to Wilson Follett, an English professor and writer. They divorced in the early 1930s. They had two daughters, Barbara and Sabra. Barbara was a child prodigy author who disappeared in 1939 at the age of 25.
Follett died in 1970 in New York City at the age of 76.
Scope and Content
Follett's papers primarily consist of personal letters, manuscripts of published and unpublished works, research materials and notes, publicity and promotional items, educational articles, photographs and postcards of her travels, and newspaper clippings.
In addition, the collection contains correspondence, writings, and newspaper clippings of her daughter, Barbara Newhall Follett.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in seven series:
Series I: Correspondence, 1919-1969
Series II: Published Materials, 1932-1941
Series III: Unpublished Materials, circa 1930s - 1966
Series IV: Publicity Materials, 1932-1939
Series V: Research Materials, 1927-1939
Series VI: Educational Materials, 1919-1935
Series VII: Barbara Newhall Follett, 1914-1933
Subjects
Follett, Barbara Newhall 1914-1939; Follett, Helen; Follett, Wilson 1887-1963; Sperry, Armstrong 1897-1976
Access Restrictions
This collection is located on-site.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
Follett, Helen Thomas Bequest 1970 M-70
Selected Related Material-- at Columbia
Barbara Newhall Follett Papers, Rare Book & Manuscript Libary, Columbia University.
Finding aid in repository; folder level control.
- Series I: Correspondence, 1919-1969
  This series consists primarily of personal letters from Helen and Wilson Follett to their very close friends, the Meserveys. Other letters are addressed to Helen from Wilson, Alice Dyer Russell, another close friend, and the Meserveys.
  - Letters from Helen Follett to the Meserveys, 1928-1931 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters from Wilson Follett to Helen Follett, 1921-1928 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters from Wilson Follett and Margaret Whipple to the Meserveys, 1928-1931 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters from the Meserveys to the Folletts, 1928-1931 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters from Ralph Blanchard to the Meserveys, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letters from Alice Dyer Russell to Helen Follett, 1933-1958 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letters from Helen Follett to Sabra Follett, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letters from 4th Grade Class to Helen Follett, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letters from Fans to Helen Follett, 1932-1940 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Business Letters, 1919-1969 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Series II: Published Materials, 1932-1944
  In this series, the papers are published manuscripts in various versions. The titles are: House Afire!, Magic Portholes, and Third-Class Ticket to Heaven.
  - House Afire!
    - Published House Afire! Story in Junior Weekly Magzines, 1941 August-September (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Notes and Correspondence, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Draft, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Manuscript, Chap. 1-10, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Manuscript, Chap. 5-6 Under Different Names, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Short Version Manuscript, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Short Version Manuscript, Part II, 65 pp., undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Short Version Manuscript, Part II, 126 pp., undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Long Version Manuscript, Part II, Book II, 151 pp., undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Random Chapters, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Third-Class Ticket to Heaven Manuscript, Chap. 1-18, circa 1938 (6 Folders) (Box 3, Folder 1 to 6)
  - Magazine Articles, 1932-1944 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Magic Portholes History, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Series III: Unpublished Materials, circa 1930s - 1966
  This series contains unpublished manuscripts of books, short stories, and poems.
  - Holiday in a Castle
    - Manuscript, First Draft, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Manuscript, Chap. 1-14, undated (2 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 2 to 3)
  - Essays about the Caribbean, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Short Stories, undated (2 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 5 to 6)
  - Poems, 1947-1966 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Mrs. Flower’s Dog Days
    - Manuscript, Chap. I-XIX, 1957 (2 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 1 to 2)
    - Manuscript 1 with corrections, circa 1957 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Manuscript 2 with corrections, circa 1957 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Bill and the Bees Manuscript and Research Materials, 1959 (2 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 5 to 6)
  - Calling America Manuscript, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Series IV: Publicity/Promotional Materials, 1932-1939
  These files contain various publicity and promotional items including a radio script, book reviews, newspaper clippings, and book jackets.
  - Magic Portholes Radio Script, 1932-1933 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Third-Class Ticket to Heaven and Magic Portholes Publicity Items, 1932-1939 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Book Reviews, 1932-1938 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1933-1937 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Series V: Research Materials, 1927-1939
  The items in this series consist of photographs, postcards and German newspaper clippings.
  - German Newspaper Clippings, 1939 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Photographs, 1927-1928 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Postcards from Germany, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Series VI: Educational Materials, 1919-1935
  This series consists of articles, notes, and a hand-made manual on education using the typewriter for elementary school children.
  - Articles and Essays on Typewriter Education, 1932 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Notes on Typewriter Education, 1932-1933 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - It’s Fun to Write! Handmade Manual, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Series VII: Barbara Newhall Follett, 1914-1933
  This series is comprised of a diary detailing Barbara’s infancy to early childhood, her writings and correspondence, and newspaper clippings.
  - Diary and Notes about Barbara, 1914-1918 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Barbara’s Writings and Letters, 1924-1933 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1927-1929 (Box 7, Folder 6)